Samuel C. Brightman Papers
Samuel C. Brightman Papers
1932-1992
Brightman, Samuel C. (Samuel Charles), 1911-
6 linear ft.
Papers of the American journalist including some war correspondence, political and political humor writings, and adult education material
2458163
Biographical History
Samuel C. Brightman was born in Lancaster, Missouri on June 22, 1911. He graduated from Washington University with a liberal arts degree and earned a degree in journalism from the University of Missouri. He worked for the St. Louis Star-Times (1933-1935), the Cincinnati Post (1935-1940), radio station KSD in St. Louis (1937), and the Louisville Courier-Journal (1940-1942) covering education and politics. In 1941 he became the Washington correspondent for the Courier-Journal and in 1942 he enlisted in the army where he served as a Public Relations Officer. He accompanied U.S. forces during the D-Day landing on Omaha Beach (his dispatches were the first ones received from the front, for which efforts he was awarded a Bronze Star) and led the press convoy into Berlin the day it fell.
After returning from Europe he worked as Special Assistant to the Housing Expediter (a federal agency established in 1946 to deal with veterans' housing and rent control), writing a number of speeches for the director. In 1947 he married Lucy Cleaver, with whom he had four children. That same year, he began a nearly twenty-year career with the Democratic National Committee, serving as associate director of publicity (1947-1952), director of publicity (1952-1957), and deputy chairman for public affairs (1957-1965). He was also managing editor and later editor of the party organ, The Democratic Digest.
In 1965 he returned to freelance PR and journalism work, covering elections and national party conventions for the three major television networks and writing for a number of publications including TV Guide, Monocle, and the New York Times.
After his retirement, Brightman became interested in adult education, particularly as it related to the political process and civic literacy. He edited a Washington, DC-based newsletter covering adult education entitled Adult and Continuing Education Today (ACET), acted as consultant to the National Council of Senior Citizens (NCSC), served on the Board of Directors of the Coalition of Adult Education Organizations (CAEO), and was an active member of the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE).
Brightman's energy, curiosity, intelligence, and sense of humor infused both his personal and his professional life throughout his long career. He died in 1992, and was buried with full military honors in Arlington National Cemetery.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Samuel C. Brightman Papers reflects its creator's lifelong interest in politics, education, and civic literacy. The collections is divided into six series. Although the majority of his writings have been collected into a single series, he often discoursed on political or humorous topics with friends and family; for this reason the researcher interested in Brightman's writings will wish to review the correspondence files as well.
Biographical and family material includes biographies written for Who's Who and other publications, family correspondence, transcripts of two oral history interviews (one for the John F. Kennedy Library and the other for the Truman Library), and a considerable amount of material on World War II, both contemporary and relating to the 40th anniversary of the Normandy Beach landings in 1984. Of particular interest are Brightman's writings, including a few letters to family and friends, a history of the army public relations office and approximately 20 pages of typescript on his experiences in Europe during and after the Omaha Beach landing on D-Day. Among Brightman's World War II memorabilia is a certificate for the Ehrenkreuzes der Deutschen Mutter (Honor Cross of the German Mother), a souvenir of Brightman's entry with the press corps into Berlin and which appears to bear the signature of Adolf Hitler.
Memorabilia contains various certificates and souvenir items, such as a 1991 Gulf War protest poster and the souvenir menu from Pan Am airlines' first transatlantic jet flight.
Correspondence-subject files consist primarily of incoming correspondence though there are some carbons and photocopies of outgoing letters. This series includes fellow journalists (Art Buchwald, Marquis Childs, Ernie Deane, Russ Baker); politicians and political entities (Democratic National Committee, Adlai Stevenson); adult educators (Alexander Charters, Mary Grefe, Malcolm Knowles, Laubach Literacy); and various civic organizations (Kettering Foundation, Annenberg Foundation, Committee for Public Broadcasting, National Council for Senior Citizens).
Writings (SCB) encompasses Brightman's journalistic and professional output over his career: articles, book proposals, a seven-article series for the Cincinnati Post recounting his travels through 1939 Europe just prior to the outbreak of war, columns from the Louisville Courier-Journal and other newspapers, press releases, speeches, and notes. Also included here are publications edited by Brightman: Adult and Continuing Education Today (ACET), the Democratic Digest, Dirge (college humor magazine), and more.
As fuel for his own writing and as ideas for his publications, Brightman amassed a substantial collection of writings by others on topics that interested him such as politics, adult education, civic literacy and the problems facing senior citizens. Writings (others) includes books, clippings, papers and articles.
Miscellaneous includes preview material for a series of audio-print courses offered by Annenberg and the Committee for Public Broadcasting and a film strip/speech for the Democratic National Committee, among other things.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically by name, type, or title.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
As originally received, the Samuel C. Brightman Papers included a number of items of potential interest to a wide range of researchers (see below). To increase their visibility, these items have been removed from the collection and cataloged separately. For more information on these items, please contact the repository listed above or search.
A complete run of the Democratic Digest, edited by Brightman (copies of the first and last issue can be found in the collection under Writings (SCB): Edited by SCB: Democratic Digest).
Programs from Democratic National Conventions in the 1950s and 1960s and various other Democratic National Party publications.
Several issues of Le Tomahawk, the 19th corps newspaper, published from Normandy Beachhead and other locations in 1944. Photocopies of the back page, which material may have been written by Brightman, can be found in Biographical and family material: World War II: Writings
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Baker, Russell, 1925-; Brightman, Samuel C. (Samuel Charles), 1911-; Buchwald, Art.; Childs, Marquis W. (Marquis William), 1903-1990.; Deane, Ernie.; Knowles, Malcolm S. (Malcolm Shepherd), 1913-1997.; Tjerandsen, Carl.; Coalition of Adult Education Organizations.; International Council for Adult Education.; National Coalition for Public Education.; National Council of Senior Citizens.; Democratic National Committee (U.S.); United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989.; Adult and Continuing Education Today.; The Brightman Report.; Democratic Digest.; Adult education.; Civics.; Continuing education.; World War, 1939-1945.; War correspondents.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Articles.; Monographs.; Photographs.; Adult educators.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Samuel C. Brightman, David Brightman (son).
Inventory
- Biographical and family material
  - Biographies (who’s who, etc), 1957; 1965,; 1972,; 1988,; 1992 (Box 1)
  - Clippings about, 1939-1995 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Brightman, Ruth (wife), 1944 (Box 1)
    - Brightman, David (son), 1991 (Box 1)
    - 80th birthday letters, 1991 (Box 1)
      See also Grefe, Mary; Gross, Ron; Knowles, Malcolm S.
  - Oral history, John F. Kennedy Library, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Oral history, Harry S. Truman Library, 1967 (Box 1)
  - University of Missouri-Columbia, 1932-1933; includes college yearbook The Savitar, 1933; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Washington University in St. Louis, 1932-1933; 1991; includes college yearbook The Hatchet, 1933; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - World War II, 1942-1991
    - Army records, 1943-1946 (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 1942; 1944,; 1964,; 1983-1984,; 1990-1991,; undated (Box 2)
    - Writings
      - "History of Public Relations Office," Samuel C. Brightman, 1945? (Box 2)
      - "Letter from Paris", 1984 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1944; undated; letters, article drafts and proposals, notes, memoranda, photocopies of back page of 19th corps newspaper Le Tomahawk (Box 2)
        Complete original issues of Le Tomahawk are cataloged. Please refer to to locate these.
    - Memorabilia, map of France, Germany [later publication]; Eagle XX Twelfth Army Group 20-year yearbook; Sept 10, 1944 issue of Yank; "Ehrenkreuzes der Deutschen Mutter" certificate, possibly signed by Hitler, with note from son David Brightman (Box 2)
      See also Memorabilia: Photographs below.
    - Misc military, 1943-1953 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified autobiographical fragments (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Alpha Tau Omega (fraternity) Gold Circle Certificate, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Gulf War protest poster, 1991 (Oversize 1)
  - "Honorary Citizen of New Orleans" certificate, 1976 (Oversize 1)
  - "Inaugural Jet Flight: Pan American" souvenir menu, 1960 (Oversize 1)
  - "Official Inaugural Program: January 20, 1961", program from LBJ's inauguration, Brightman's name stamped on front in gold (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Adult and Continuing Education Today, 1979; 1985,; 1990 (Box 2)
    See also Writings: Edited by SCB: Adult and Continuing Education Today.
  - American Newspaper Publisher’s Association (ANPA) Foundation, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Annenberg/Committee for Public Broadcasting, 1986; 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    See also Miscellaneous: Annenberg/CPB Audio-Print Course Collection preview material.
  - Baker, Russ (New York Times), 1973; 1977,; 1979,; 1984 (Box 2)
  - Baldwin, Dave, 1973; 1977,; 1991,; undated (Box 3)
  - Barrett, Charles M., 1977 (Box 3)
  - Basic Choices Inc., 1988-1990; undated; includes copy of The Millennium Survival Kit (Box 3)
  - Buchwald, Art, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Buffkins, Archie L., 1977 (Box 3)
  - CBS, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Charters, Alexander N., 1989; 1991 (Box 3)
  - Childs, Marquis, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Coalition of Adult Education Organizations (CAEO), 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Congress of the United States, 1982; 1984,; 1986 (Box 3)
  - Deane, Ernie, 1988-1989; 1991 (Box 3)
  - Democratic Party
    See also Democratic Digest.
    - Campaign materials, 1956 (Box 3)
    - The Democrat, 1961-1964 (Box 3)
    - Democratic National Committee, 1952-1953; 1957,; 1959-1960,; 1963,; 1971,; undated (Box 3)
      See also Writings (SCB): Authored by SCB: Press releases.
  - Dorland, James (SUNY Morrisville), 1991 (Box 3)
  - Draves, Bill, See Learning Resources Network (LERN).
  - Edelson, Alfred, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Elderhostel, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Elmer [Lower?], 1944 (Box 3)
  - Fischer, Ken, 1977 (Box 3)
  - GED, ca 1986?; includes Brightman's notes for possible book (Box 3)
  - Godbey, Gordon, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Grefe, Mary, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Gross, Ron, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Hackethorn, Jack, 1991; undated (Box 4)
  - Institute for Development of Educational Achievement (IDEA), 1991 (Box 4)
  - International Council for Adult Education (ICAE), undated (Box 4)
  - International Reading Association (IRA), 1989-1991 (Box 4)
  - [John F.] Kennedy Library, 1975 (Box 4)
    See also Biographical and family material: Oral history, John F. Kennedy Library.
  - Kettering Foundation, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Knowles, Malcolm, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Laubach Literacy, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Learning Resources Network (LERN), 1984; 1986,; 1989,; 1993 (Box 4)
  - Michelson, Edward J., 1990 (Box 4)
  - Millennium Survival Kit, See Basic Choices Inc..
  - Monocle, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
    See also Writings (SCB): Authored by SCB: Articles.
  - National Coalition for Public Education (NCPE), 1991; includes survey on violations of the separation of church and state (Box 4)
  - National Council of Senior Citizens (NCSC), 1991 (Box 4)
  - National Council for Social Studies (NCSS), 1991 (Box 4)
  - National Issues Forums, 1987 (Box 4)
  - National Museum of American History (Smithsonian), 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - National Press Club, 1986; 1991,; undated (Box 4)
  - New York Times, 1972; undated (Box 4)
    See also Baker, Russ.
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), 1998; certificates of origin (Box 4)
  - Ohliger, John, See Basic Choices Inc.
  - Political TV [supplied title], 1989-1991; undated; includes clippings, notes, draft of article? (Box 4)
  - Republican National Committee, 1953; 1965 (Box 4)
  - Ross, Donald S., 1977 (Box 4)
  - Stern, Milton (UC Berkeley), 1991; includes text of two speeches, both on adult/continuing education (Box 5)
  - Stern, Philip M., 1965; 1977,; 1990 (Box 5)
  - Stevenson, Adlai, 1952 (Box 5)
  - Stewart, David W., 1991 (Box 5)
  - Stillwell, Hamilton, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Study circles, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Tjerandsen, Carl, 1983; 1989; includes monograph, "How Stands the Union? The University and Public Responsibility" (1983) (Box 5)
  - TV Guide, 1972 (Box 5)
    See also Writings (SCB): Authored by SCB: Articles
  - Unger, Paul, 1967 (Box 5)
  - United States Department of Commerce, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - University of Missouri, 1989; 1991 (Box 5)
  - Vermont, 1978; "Adult Literacy Day" declaration (Box 5)
  - "Voices and Visions: A Television Course on Modern American Poetry", See Annenberg/Committee for Public Broadcasting.
  - W—, Roy, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Ward, Lester, 1975; undated (Box 5)
  - White House, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Writings by Brightman
  - Authored by SCB
    - Articles, typescripts and/or drafts
      - Titled, A-Z (Box 5)
      - Untitled, A-Z by first word (Box 5)
    - Book proposals (Box 5)
    - The Brightman Report, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - Clippings
      - Cincinnati Post, 1939; SCB's experiences travelling through Europe just before Hitler's invasion of Poland (Box 6)
      - Louisville Courier-Journal, humor writing (Box 6)
      - Louisville Courier-Journal, political writing (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous humor (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous politics (Box 6)
    - Papers (Box 6)
    - Press releases, Democratic National Committee (Box 6)
    - Republican National Convention coverage (Box 6)
    - "Sam Brightman’s Washington", column from ACET (Box 6)
    - Speeches
      - Given by SCB, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Written by SCB, written while SBC worked as special assistant to the National Housing Agency, Office of the Housing Expediter (Box 7)
    - Various topics
      - ACET series (Box 7)
      - Civic literacy (Box 7)
        See also Correspondence-subject files: Tjerandsen, Carl; Writings by others: Papers and articles: Civic literacy.
      - "Nuts and Bolts" (Box 7)
    - Fragments (Box 7)
    - Notes (Box 7)
      See also Correspondence-subject files: GED and Correspondence-subject files: Political TV.
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Edited by SCB
    - Adult and Continuing Education Today (ACET), 1971; 1984-1991; 9 folders (Box 7, 8)
    - Democratic Digest, 1953; 1961; first and last issues only, others have been removed and sent for cataloging. See to locate these items. (Box 8)
      See also Monocle.
    - Dirge, 1931; college humor magazine (Box 8)
    - The New America, 1956; official publication of 1956 Democratic campaign (Box 8)
    - Politics Today, 1971-1972 (Box 8)
    - Women Today, 1971 (Box 8)
- Writings by others
  - Books
    Most are publications of the Democratic National Comittee.
    - The 1956 Democratic Fact Book: The Issues and the Record 1952-1956 (Box 8)
    - The 1960 Democratic Fact Book (Box 8)
    - Democratic National Convention Program, 1964 (Oversize 1)
    - Campaign Documents 1956 (Box 8)
    - Cannon, Clarence / Democratic Manual for the Democratic National Convention, 1952 (Box 8)
    - Cannon, Clarence / Democratic Manual for the Democratic National Convention of 1960 (Box 8)
    - Cannon, Clarence / Democratic Manual for the Democratic National Convention of 1968 (Box 8)
    - CBS News Campaign ’72: Republican National Convention, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Citizens’ Research Foundation publications, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - "Financing a Better Election System," Committee for Economic Development, 1968 (Box 9)
    - How to Win in 1952: Democratic National Committee Campaign Handbook (Box 9)
    - Hupman, Richard D. / Nomination and Election of the President and Vice President of the United States, 1972 (Box 9)
    - Leibholz, Gerhard / Jahrbuch des Offentlichen Rechts der Gegenwart: Neue Folge/Band 17., circa 1967 (Box 9)
  - Clippings
    - Campaigns and the media (Box 9)
    - Education (Box 9)
    - Health care (Box 9)
      See also National Council of Senior Citizens (NCSE).
    - Politics (Box 9)
    - Senior citizens (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Printed material
    - Adult Education (Box 10)
      See also Charters, Alexander N.; Ross, Donald S.; Stewart, David W.; Stern, Milton, in the Correspondence-subject files.
    - Civic literacy (Box 10)
      See also Correspondence-subject files: Tjerandsen, Carl and Writings by Brightman: Authored by SCB: Various topics: Civic literacy drafts.
    - International Interaction, 1973-1977; bulletin of International Education Project
    - "People and the Press" (Box 10)
    - "Tell It Like It Was: Senior Speaker’s Fact Book" (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous
- Miscellaneous
  - Annenberg/CPB Audio-Print Course Collection preview material, 6 cassette tapes and publicity brochures, in vinyl case (Box 10)
  - "6-Cent Register and Vote Commemorative U.S. Postage Stamp: June 27, 1968" (Oversize 1)
  - "Democratic Communication film strip" with accompanying speech (Oversize 1)
  - Unidentified cassette tape (Oversize 1)